<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: review, | Aditya Patil]]></title>
  <link href="http://amp101.github.com/blog/categories/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://amp101.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-17T23:01:55+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://amp101.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Aditya Patil]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[As Good As It Gets]]></title>
    <link href="http://amp101.github.com/blog/2007/03/26/as-good-as-it-gets/"/>
    <updated>2007-03-26T20:20:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://amp101.github.com/blog/2007/03/26/as-good-as-it-gets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>IMDB Rating: 7.8/10</p>

<p>Cast of characters:</p>

<p>Jack Nicholson as Melvin Udall<br/>
Helen Hunt as Caroll Connelly  <br/>
Greg Kinnear as Simon Bishop</p>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>This movie is a touching comedy about three New Yorkers, three unhappy people, who have been condemned by destiny to be whacked and slapped more often than what would be their fair share. It is about a writer (Udall), who has Obsessive Compulsive Disorder (OCD). He is mean, angry and frustrated; but writes romantic stories for a living. It is about this diffident, young homosexual painter (Simon), who has a strange kind of honesty about him. And a not so young, single mother (Caroll) who has somewhere lost herself between nursing an acutely ill son and working as a waitress.</p>

<h2>The First Scene</h2>

<p>Simon’s ill-mannered pooch is contemplating blasphemy at the corner of a wall with a hind leg raised in the air, outside the front door of Udall’s apartment. This certainly does not go well with Udall. He discourages the dog in his characteristic mean and threatening manner, talking and smiling to him, inviting the dog to join him in the elevator, perhaps to dispose him off in the bustle of the mean city outside. The dog is not easily convinced. Udall picks him up, and the pooch takes advantage of his elevated position to do what Udall dreads. A disgusted Udall, enraged with the dog’s audacity, pushes him down the garbage chute; a smug smile adorns his countenance as he naively thinks that he has rid himself of this nuisance forever.</p>

<h2>Udall</h2>

<p>He is a queer character. He does not walk in a straight line, but chooses to dodge imaginary lines on the floor beneath. He, as the rest of the world, does not simply switch on the light, or lock the door. He will switch the light on and off five times – on, off, on, off and finally, on. Ditto for the lock. The cabinet above his washbasin is stacked with dozens of newly packed soap bars. He washes his hands with two new soap bars under blistering hot water. An extreme case of OCD; he is in dire need of the services of a professional and competent psychiatrist. At the same time, he is also an extremely popular writer of ideal, romantic stories – painting illusions of true love and companionship - the kind that are supposedly popular with a section of the female half of the species.</p>

<h2>Tragedy in its various forms</h2>

<p>The storyline is weaved around a tragic accident that takes place with Simon. He becomes the victim of a merciless attack, inside his own home, by some hooligans. This not only leaves his face scarred beyond recognition but also unsettles his life. The resulting medical expenses leave him bankrupt. He will have to give up his apartment and studio. His fortunes hit so low that even his own dog begins to ignores him. Caroll likewise has her own problems to deal with. She struggles to treat her son’s asthma and allergy condition which leave him incapacitated. She is frustrated, bitter and tired.</p>

<p>However, things do not reamain dark and dreary forever. This is cinema, afterall. Udall, the hopeless cynic discovers that he has tender feelings for Caroll. He becomes a nicer person. The sarcasm and meanness withdraw from his personality. He becomes friends with Simon. He, also, does something spectacular for Caroll and her son. These three people find companionship, support and love in each other. And live happily every after. <Sigh/>.</p>

<p>It's a feel good movie that's supposed to leave you warm and happy on the inside. Must watch if you are a Jack Nicholson fan.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Shawshank Redemption]]></title>
    <link href="http://amp101.github.com/blog/2006/01/17/the-shawshank-redemption/"/>
    <updated>2006-01-17T22:18:00+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://amp101.github.com/blog/2006/01/17/the-shawshank-redemption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Theme</h2>

<p>The movie is a touching depiction of prison life. Andrew Dufresne, vice president in a big bank, has been convicted of the murder of his wife and her lover. He is innocent of the crime but in the face of strong circumstantial evidence is sentenced to two back to back life sentences in a high security prison - Shawshank. It is the end of life for him, at least the life that he has ever known. Like Andrew almost every other man in Shawshank knows that he is probably never going to see his friends, family and loved ones again. These people have no hope and they have no future. But life is such a beautiful phenomenon that even in the face of such a dreary, monotonous existence, they try to find a balance. To look at these people, one would hardly think that they are doomed – they joke, play, eat, chat – they live normal lives, or as normal a life as they can.</p>

<p>Andrew tries to make a difference in a variety of ways. He writes a letter to the state senate every week asking for funds for the prison library. After six years, they get tired and sends him some old books and two hundred dollars and plead him to stop writing those letters. Andrew then starts writing two letters every week. Eventually, he is able to build a large library with books, music records and other facilities for the prisoners. He teaches the prisoners and helps some of them pass High School. He even helps the guards fill their tax returns. The only thing he is probably trying to do is to make his life worthwhile.</p>

<p>Andrew makes friends with Ellis Boyd Redding (Red for short). He is a philosophical character and his monologues about prison life with the soft melancholy music playing in the background are touching as well as insightful.</p>

<blockquote><p>“When they put you in that cell and those bars slam home, that’s when you know its for real. Whole life blown away in the blink of an eye and nothing left but all the time in the world to think about it.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Red has another interesting quote about an old man called Brooks, who's finally released after 50 years at Shawshank. Is Brooks happy at the prospect of freedom? As Red says,</p>

<blockquote><p>“Brooks is institutionalized.In here he is an important man. Outside he is nothing. Just a used up con with arthritis in both hands. These Walls are funny. First you hate ‘em and then you get used to ‘em. Enough time passes and you get to depend on ‘em. That’s institutionalized. They send you here for life and that’s exactly what they take.”</p></blockquote>

<p>Simply beautiful!</p>

<p>The ending of the movie is a fantastic surprise and I wouldn’t want to take anything away from those who haven’t seen the film.</p>

<h2>Trivia</h2>

<ul>
<li>The film was not very successful when it was released in theatres but later on through the home video market it became a huge hit</li>
<li>It has been voted as the second greatest movie ever made in Internet Movie Database’s Top 250 Films of all time after the Godfather.</li>
<li>It was nominated for seven Oscars – Best Movie, Best Actor (Morgan Freeman), Best Director, Best Adapted Screenplay, Best Cinematography, Best Editing, Best Original Score, and Best Sound. It failed to win even a single Oscar.</li>
<li>It is based on Stephen King's novella "Rita Hayworth and Shawshank Redemption"</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
